in this video we're going to talk about
gravity
what is gravity
gravity is a force that brings matter
together
now you know that if you place let's say
a rock above the ground
you know that rock is going to fall
towards the ground and the reason for
that is gravity
gravity causes objects to fall
now gravity is the force
and that force brings the rock down
towards the earth
but what you may not have known is that
the earth actually accelerates towards
the rock
however because the mass of the earth
is so much more greater than a rock
it doesn't appear that the earth is
moving its acceleration it's
insignificant
because the rock's mass is so small it
has a much larger acceleration
and the rock it accelerates towards the
ground
at this rate 9.8 meters per second
squared
so this is known as gravitational
acceleration
this value
tells us the rate at which the speed of
the rock changes every second
so every second
the velocity of the rock it changes by
9.8 meters per second
so it's decreasing by 9.8 meters per
second since it's going down in the
negative y direction
now let's talk more about gravity
let's say
this is the earth
and let's say
this is the moon
gravity brings matter together
the earth
feels a force that accelerated towards
the moon
and the moon fills an equal but opposite
force
that pulls it towards the earth
and so these forces they have the same
magnitude
and to calculate this force
it's equal to the gravitational constant
times
the mass of the earth times the mass of
the moon
divided by
the distance between their centers
which is r
so r is the distance between the center
of the earth
and the center of the moon
and so using that equation you can
calculate the gravitational force
between the earth and the moon
this equation is known as the universal
law of gravitation
so as you can see
the force of gravity
is proportional
to the masses of the two objects for
instance let's say
if you have a rock and if you have let's
say a book
the force of gravity between these two
objects is not noticeable
the rock is not going to
slide towards the book and the reason
for that is because their masses are so
small
for gravity to be significant
you need masses on a planetary scale
you need huge masses
for it to
be important
as you increase the mass of a planet the
gravitational force that it exerts on
other planets increases
the second factor is distance
notice that the distance is on the
bottom of the equation
so as you increase the distance between
a planet and another planet the
gravitational forces acting on those
planets decreases
so the moon has a greater effect on
planet earth compared to pluto because
pluto is so far away
so gravity
plays a role
on objects that are nearby
objects that are far away gravity
weakens greatly
in fact as you double the distance
between two planets the gravitational
force reduces by a factor of four
if you double one of the masses of the
planets the gravitational force will
double
now it turns out that the gravitational
force
is the same
as the weight force
and let me illustrate that
so let's say
this is the earth
and let's say
we have
a 20 kilogram
block resting on the earth
now what is the weight force of that 20
kilogram block
the weight force is simply the mass
times the gravitational acceleration
so it's going to be
the mass of the block which is 20
kilograms
times the gravitational acceleration
of 9.8 meters per second squared
so 20 times 9.8
that gives us a weight force
of
196 newtons
now let's see if we can get the same
answer
using the universal law of gravitation
formula
so the formula was f
is equal to g
m one
m two over r squared
now g
is the universal gravitation constant
which is 6.67
times 10 to the negative 11
and it's newtons
times square meters divided by square
kilograms
now the mass of the earth that's 5.98
times 10 to the 24
kilograms
the mass of the block m2 is 20 kilograms
and the distance between the center of
the earth
and the surface of the earth because the
block is on the surface
that's the radius of the earth which you
can call re and you can look up this
value in a textbook it's 6.38
times 10 to the 6
meters and we need to square it
so go ahead and type these numbers into
your scientific device
all right give me a few seconds i'm
almost done
so the answer that i got
is
195.98 newtons
so as you can see
the gravitational force or the weight
force is about 196 newtons
now of course these numbers that i'm
using are rounded figures so that's why
it's not exactly the same
but it should be the same so this is
approximately 196 newtons
so the weight force
and gravity or the gravitational force
they're identical
now how do we get this number
how do we calculate the gravitational
acceleration
well let's look at these two equations
the weight force is mg
and the force of gravity
is g
m1
m2 over r squared
now we said that these two they're the
same
which means that
we can set
these two portions of the equation
equal to each other
so let's do that g
m1 over m2 i mean times m2 over r
squared
let's set it equal to mg
now all we need to do is cancel one of
the masses
particularly
it really doesn't matter which mass you
cancel
m1 or m2
so the gravitational acceleration of a
planet
is the gravitational constant times the
mass of the planet
over r squared
so let's calculate it for the earth
so we're going to use the mass of the
earth
and
the radius of the earth
so g is 6.67 times 10 to the minus 11.
the mass of the earth we said it's 5.98
times 10 to the 24 kilograms
and the radius of the earth
is this number again in
meters so go ahead and type that in
so you should get 9.799
meters per second squared
which you can round that to
9.8 meters per second squared
and so this formula
helps us to calculate the gravitational
acceleration
of any planet
it could be a moon it could be a planet
it could be
a star like the sun
you can use this to calculate the
gravitational acceleration of any object
now that's basically it for this video
that's all i got so if you like this
video
feel free to subscribe to this channel
and don't forget to click on that
notification bell
in addition for those of you who want
more math problems
on gravity and
the universal law of gravitation i have
another video that
have a lot of problems that you can work
on and what i'm gonna do
is i'm gonna post a few links
in the description section of this video
that will point you towards uh more
problems like finding the gravitational
force finding the distance between
planets
and um
stuff like that you'll see it
and not only that i'm gonna have some
other topics related to gravity like how
to find the speed of a satellite in
orbit
and uh some other problems on
centripetal force
and kepler's third laws and just other
topics that relates to gravity space and
planets and
things like that so when you get a
chance feel free to check out those
links below
and whatever you do don't forget to
subscribe to this channel
now i do have other topics besides
physics
i do have a playlist on physics you can
check out my channel if you want more
info on that
i have a playlist on chemistry
algebra trig geometry
calculus pre-calculus
so basically the common topics that you
encounter in school i have a playlist on
that stuff if you need help on that so
feel free to take a look at that when
you get a chance thanks for watching